<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before King Charles, March 27. 1627. Being the anniuersary of his Maiesties inauguration: by Isacc [sic] Bargraue, Doctor in Diuinity, then chaplaine to his Maiestie in attendance: and Deane of Canterbury: by His Maiesties speciall command</title>
            <author>Bargrave, Isaac, 1586-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120694</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21396</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1019:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before King Charles, March 27. 1627. Being the anniuersary of his Maiesties inauguration: by Isacc [sic] Bargraue, Doctor in Diuinity, then chaplaine to his Maiestie in attendance: and Deane of Canterbury: by His Maiesties speciall command</title>
                  <author>Bargrave, Isaac, 1586-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 [i.e. 21], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt, for Peter Paxton, and are to be sold at his shop at the Angell in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 21 misnumbered 19.</note>
                  <note>Quire A inner forme is in two settings: A3v line 1 has (1) "easy" or (2) "easie".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21396:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21396:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE KING CHARLES, <hi>March</hi> 27. 1627. Being the Anniuerſary of his MAIESTIES Inauguration:</p>
            <p>BY ISACC BARGRAVE, Doctor in Diuinity, Then Chaplaine to his MAIESTIE in Attendance: And DEANE of CANTERBVERY:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> His MAIESTIES ſpeciall Command.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt,</hi> for <hi>Peter Paxton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Angell in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21396:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21396:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. Sam. 15. verſ. 23</bibl>
               <q>Rebellion is as the ſinne of Witch-craft, and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the wickedneſſe of Idolatry.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR all-wiſe <hi>God,</hi> who made Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the meaſure of his creation, placed man among the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures here below, as the chiefe Adminiſtrator of order. Man was then <hi>planted as a tree by the riuers of waters, Pſal.</hi> 1. 3. and, had hee growne on in the order wherein hee was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>his leafe had not withered, he had brought forth his fruit in his ſeaſon, and whatſoeuer he had done, had proſpered.</hi> But alas! diſobedience and order could neuer long dwell together. The worme of pride had no ſooner corrupted the roote of mankinde, but inſtantly this goodly tree loſt both <hi>leaues</hi> and <hi>fruit</hi> too; nay all the <hi>ſtemmes</hi> iſſuing from that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>ſtocke,</hi> haue euer ſince prooued naturally fitter for infernall fuell, then for the ſeruice of <hi>Gods</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Man in his corrupt nature, ioynes in this with the other creatures; <hi>non vult domari.</hi> If the wind be ſtayed in his courſe, it will roote vp the ſtrongeſt Oakes: if the water in her motion, ſhee will ſwell, and ouerſwell the bankes. And though God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be the Commander, yet rather then men will
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21396:3"/> want their will, they will ſummon a whole <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt him, as in the 2. Pſalme, <hi>The Rulers taking counſell together, and the people imagining a vaine thing againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Let vs breake their bonds aſunder, and cast away their cords from vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doth wretched man, by endeauouring to caſt off the lighter yoake of <hi>Gods</hi> Law, pull vpon himſelfe an heauier: The law of his owne <hi>lust</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> walking on thorow the paths of wilfull diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to vnauoidable deſtruction. To cure which ſwelling ſore, as <hi>God</hi> holding his <hi>Scepter</hi> in heauen, labours by all the meanes both of his mercies and iudgements, to retract vs from that fatall way: ſo he eſtabliſheth <hi>Scepters</hi> on earth, as a ready meanes to helpe to reduce vs to the perfection of our firſt rule: making the duty of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Table, a ſtep to our duty of the <hi>firſt,</hi> ſubduing our will to the will of <hi>man</hi> on earth, that ſo he may the better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due vs to his <hi>owne</hi> Will in heauen. Firſt, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualuable bleſſing vpon a Land, God giues vs a <hi>King;</hi> and then as the power of that bleſſing, he preſcribes <hi>obedience</hi> to our <hi>King.</hi> So that in reference to the <hi>God</hi> of order, as we ſhould eſteeme no day happier then this whereon <hi>God</hi> hath bleſt vs with a true <hi>Succeſſour</hi> of his <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>iuſt</hi> and <hi>pious King;</hi> ſo can there be no <hi>ſacrifice</hi> fitter for this happy I D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, then the ſacrifice of <hi>obedience</hi> both to <hi>God</hi> and to our <hi>King.</hi> The breach of which duty to <hi>either</hi> in their degree, being no leſſe then <hi>as the ſin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and as the wickedneſſe of Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>faith</hi> is the cleereſt gloſſe of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21396:3"/> 
               <hi>obedience</hi> the beſt expoſition of the <hi>Law, better then</hi> the beſt of <hi>ſacrifices, the fat of Lambes,</hi> as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſe. Better, becauſe the wickedeſt man aliue may <hi>offer Sacrifice;</hi> none can <hi>obey</hi> but the <hi>good.</hi> Nay, euen from good <hi>Abraham, God</hi> refuſed the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but accepted the <hi>obedience.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, <hi>diſobedience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Deputies,</hi> though it proceed from <hi>weakeneſſe,</hi> is a ſinne. But if it ſwell to <hi>ſtubbornneſſe</hi> and <hi>rebellion,</hi> it is a great ſinne; great as <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is the <hi>worſt</hi> kinde of ſinne; great as <hi>Witch-craft</hi> (which in bleſſed King IAMES his phraſe) is the <hi>worſt</hi> kinde of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the truth of which aſſertion, that I may leade you thorow the path of methode, I ſhall firſt view it generally and in <hi>Theſi,</hi> as it may concerne all men, <hi>High and low, rich and poore, one with another.</hi> Then particularly, and in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> as it ſtrikes at the <hi>offendors</hi> in this Chapter, <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>people.</hi> In the generall, we ſhall finde firſt in <hi>poſitiuo,</hi> that <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> is both a <hi>ſinne</hi> and the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all ſinne: heare therefore and auoid it. Secondly, in <hi>comparatiuo,</hi> that it is the <hi>foulest</hi> of ſinnes, euen as <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Bee pleaſed to hearken, that you may hate it.</p>
            <p>A ſubiect (I confeſſe) it is of ſuch importance and authoritie, that none ſo fit as <hi>Samuel</hi> himſelfe, to haue deliuered it. Fitter had it beene for me with <hi>Aaron</hi> to haue ſtood below among the people: but ſince with <hi>Moſes</hi> I was ſummoned vp to the mount, I would not fall within the cenſure of mine owne text.</p>
            <p>Now, to follow theſe ſteps as they are laid, and ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21396:4"/> to make the paſſage more eaſie, firſt in <hi>poſitiuo</hi> wee will conſider the <hi>nature of rebellion</hi> in generall.</p>
            <p>It is a common rule in Diuinity, that in all the ſonnes of decayed <hi>Adam,</hi> that whatſoeuer is moſt <hi>naturall,</hi> is to be ſuſpected as moſt <hi>ſinfull.</hi> Now, by nature wee are all as oxen vnpliable to the yoake. <hi>Animam Regis quis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> portat:</hi> that which is the hope of the <hi>Iewes</hi> at the comming of their <hi>Meſsiah, Euery mechanick would be a King, no man would be a Subiect.</hi> Man naturally hath ſuch a will as cannot be ſubiect. We are all borne <hi>the enemies of God,</hi> and as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly<note place="margin">Rom 8 7. Iudges 19 22.</note> ſonnes of <hi>Belial. Viri abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iugo,</hi> like an vntamed <hi>heyfer</hi> we are euer kicking againſt our Maker. <hi>Multi in Ieſum, pauci in Dominum;</hi> many will willingly<note place="margin">Ier. 31.</note> heare of God as a <hi>Sauiour,</hi> but if you propound him as a <hi>Commander,</hi> their anſwer is ready, <hi>our tongues are our owne, who is Lord ouer vs?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 12. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it fares with <hi>God,</hi> and worſe with his <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Eſt multis the ſaurus in lingua ſitus, vt quaestui ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plaurus Paenul.</note> 
               <hi>male loqui melioribus.</hi> Though the earth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp <hi>Core</hi> and his complices, yet too many of their generation remaine ſtill: men, whoſe <hi>purity</hi> conſiſts in <hi>parity,</hi> whoſe <hi>conſcience</hi> in <hi>diſobedience. Wherefore ſhall any men lift themſelues vp aboue the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16. 3.</note> 
               <hi>congregation of the Lord?</hi> Well; whence this <hi>fruite</hi> proceedes the <hi>roote</hi> will demonſtrate. Euen when <hi>God</hi> on the Mount had taken obedience for his <hi>text,</hi> then did the Diuell diuert his people to <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>rebellion.</hi> Euen when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was giuing <hi>Iudas</hi> the bleſſed bread of ſaluation, then did Satan per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to plot his <hi>Sauiours</hi> deſtruction. Thus did both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell</hi> beginne with <hi>oppoſition</hi> a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21396:4"/> plaine argument, that it is the worke of the Diuell the Author of <hi>rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A truth, which will yet reflect far more cleerly, if you behold it in <hi>Comparatiuo,</hi> whether you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>rebellion</hi> with the contrary vertue <hi>Obedience,</hi> as in the verſe before; or with the <hi>paralell vices</hi> in the text, <hi>witchcraft</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Firſt, by the rule of S. <hi>Gregory, ex aduerſo melius oſtenditur,</hi> the light will beſt appeare through the contrary vertue. Now, by the rule of contraries, as <hi>Arist. Eth.</hi> 8. ſayes, <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus actus virtutis opponitur maximo vitio, et mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus minimo.</hi> If <hi>obedience</hi> be the <hi>beſt</hi> of vertues, then rebellion is the <hi>worst</hi> of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Looke then firſt in the old <hi>Law, Sacrifice</hi> was the <hi>beſt</hi> in that: yet behold, <hi>obedience is better then Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> And the Adeps, the fat, was the <hi>beſt</hi> part of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> (God alwaies reſerued that for himſelfe) yet ſee, <hi>obedience</hi> is <hi>better</hi> then <hi>the fat of Lambes.</hi> To offer many Sacrifices with the Papiſts, without <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> is little other in their owne <hi>Tostats</hi> phraſe then <hi>ſtudium nequitiae,</hi> a kind of deuotion by which a man takes much paines to offend God. <hi>Sacrifice?</hi> Alas, that was commanded as the meere <hi>Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter</hi> to <hi>obedience. Obedience</hi> is good in it ſelfe, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> only in reſpect to the Law that commanded it. <hi>Obedience</hi> did that which all the legall <hi>Sacrifices</hi> could not doe, it ranſomd vs from the power of the Diuell. In <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> beaſts were killed; in <hi>obedience,</hi> the luſts of our owne fleſh are mortified: to <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> our beaſtly affections, muſt needs be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to offer beaſts. As Faith is the beſt of the <hi>Theologicall,</hi> ſo <hi>obedience</hi> the chiefeſt of the <hi>morall</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21396:5"/> vertues: Nay Legall Iuſtice which is nothing elſe but the <hi>obedience</hi> of the whole Law, is <hi>omnis virtus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> nay it excels, ſaith he, all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, <hi>quantum lucifer inter Aſtra,</hi> as the morning Star excels all others in beauty. In a word; actiue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h one, is the <hi>Father,</hi> and paſſiue, the <hi>Mother</hi> of all vertue. And therefore if Chriſts example will mooue vs, <hi>perdidit vitam, ne perderet obedientiam,</hi> he choſe rather to loſe his life then his obedience.</p>
            <p>Why, ſee then the iſſue of this firſt compariſon; if <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his Law, be not onely a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but <hi>omnis virtus,</hi> all vertue: then rebellion to <hi>God</hi> and his Law is not only a ſinne, but <hi>omne vitium,</hi> all ſinne: ſo that take it generally, and to compare any ſinne with it, is to compare a <hi>part</hi> with the whole.</p>
            <p>Nor is this yet enough. The <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aggrauates it in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> text, by a ſecond compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; with the <hi>paralell ſinnes,</hi> as well as with the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vertues.</hi> Rebellion cauſeth all ſinne in <hi>generall,</hi> and is as great as the fouleſt ſinnes in <hi>particular,</hi> euen as <hi>witchcraft and Idolatry.</hi> Such is the monſtrous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mans <hi>diſobedience,</hi> that ſimple and poſitiue notions cannot expreſſe it, it muſt be heightned by compariſons; nor can euery comparatine reach it: nothing can arriue at the top of mans ſinne, but the ſinne of man; and no ſinnes will paralell <hi>rebellion,</hi> but thoſe of <hi>witchcraft</hi> or <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In taking the height of which compariſon, <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> and others conceiue, that <hi>Samuel</hi> here aymd not at the <hi>equality</hi> of the ſinnes, but of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but to him that well eyes it, it will appeare plainely, that as the Prophet had ſpoken before of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21396:5"/> the contrary vertue <hi>obedience</hi> it ſelfe, ſo here he ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med directly at the <hi>ſinne</hi> it ſelfe; that <hi>rebellion</hi> was as the wickedneſſe of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Witch-craft</hi> being an high kinde of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I neede not compare them ſeuerally; the greater implyes the leſſer. Nor are we to expect, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon ſhould runne euen vpon all feet: It is not <hi>comparatio aequalitatis, ſed ſimilitudinis,</hi> tis a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>quality,</hi> not of <hi>equality.</hi> But firſt, as all com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paratiues ſhould doe, theſe ſinnes they meete in <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oco,</hi> they both communicate in the ſame <hi>forme;</hi> they are both <hi>primarily</hi> ſinnes againſt the <hi>firſt</hi> Table; both haue the ſame <hi>beginning</hi> from <hi>Infidelity;</hi> both the ſame <hi>end,</hi> the contempt of <hi>Gods Ordinance.</hi> The Romiſh <hi>Idolater</hi> adores the true <hi>God</hi> with falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: ſo doth he who worſhips <hi>God</hi> according to the will of man. The <hi>Witch,</hi> hee makes the deuill his <hi>God:</hi> little better doth he that makes his owne will his <hi>God.</hi> Idolatry? why, tis the <hi>higheſt</hi> of ſinnes, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>God,</hi> not onely as he is a Law-giuer, ſo the breach of the <hi>ſecond</hi> table is againſt <hi>God:</hi> but a ſinne <hi>directly</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> as he is <hi>God:</hi> And ſo doth the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> oppoſe him. The <hi>Idolater</hi> makes a plurality of <hi>gods,</hi> and that includes a <hi>nullity; Dicite plures, dicite nullum:</hi> and neere as good no <hi>God,</hi> as no <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> In the breach of the <hi>Sabbath, Gods</hi> honour is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed; in <hi>Idolatry</hi> his eſſence is denied; In ſwearing <hi>Gods</hi> name is <hi>vilified;</hi> in <hi>Idolatry</hi> tis annihilated. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing, vilifying, denying, annihilating, all are included in rebelling. In <hi>Idolatry</hi> they offer to <hi>Idols;</hi> in <hi>Witch-craft</hi> they ſacrifice to <hi>deuils;</hi> yet behold, <hi>rebellion</hi> a ſinne comparatiue to <hi>both;</hi> nay, ſuperlatiue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21396:6"/> aboue both, and the cauſe of both. For were there no <hi>rebellion</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Law,</hi> there could be neither <hi>Witchcraft</hi> nor <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this generall <hi>gloſſe</hi> ſeeme yet too large, let vs now contract it in the particular, and conſider the truth of this compariſon in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> the ſinne here of <hi>Saul</hi> and of his <hi>people.</hi> Which being done, tis to be feared leſt finding <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>rebellion,</hi> we ſhall finde <hi>our ſelues</hi> likewiſe in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> both guilty of a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſinne, like to that of <hi>witchcraft</hi> or <hi>idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in <hi>Sauls</hi> offence cleerely characterd in this Chapter, two points are moſt remarkable. His foule <hi>commiſsion,</hi> his falſe <hi>ſubmiſsion.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by two cleere circumſtances: The <hi>worth</hi> of the Gifts which God gaue him; the <hi>vnworthineſſe</hi> of his ends, for which he rebelled againſt him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for his <hi>perſon;</hi> there was not a more come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> among all the ſonnes of Iſrael. Secondly, for his<note place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 9. 2.</note> 
               <hi>place;</hi> from the leaſt Family, and the ſmalleſt Tribe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he was aduanced to be the <hi>Head of the Tribes of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> Thirdly, For his endowments; The <hi>Spirit</hi> of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the <hi>Lord</hi> came extraordinarily vpon him, and hee prophecied. Thus much did God giue h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and therefore expected to receiue much from him. He did from him, he doth from vs. <hi>Donorum promptus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>quidem Author, ſed importunus exactor. God requires his owne with vſury, Matth.</hi> 25. 27. Where <hi>God</hi> performes mighty workes, hee lookes for effectuall <hi>obedience.</hi> Otherwiſe woe to <hi>Iſrael</hi> here, <hi>woe to Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin, woe to Bethſaida,</hi> it <hi>ſhall bee more tolerable for Trye and Sidon then for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, <hi>O Engliſh Iſrael,</hi> let the ſtaine of <hi>Iſraels</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21396:6"/> vnthankfull <hi>rebellion</hi> mooue thee to ready <hi>obedience.</hi> The Lord hath exalted thee as the <hi>King among the nations.</hi> For temporall bleſsings, <hi>hee hath hitherto made faſt the barres of thy gates.</hi> Whereas other more thankfull people haue beene oppreſſed with bloody warre; <hi>Peace</hi> and the Princes of peace haue <hi>flouriſhed within our palaces. Our wiues haue beene as the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vine, and our children as the oliue branches about our table.</hi> The <hi>God</hi> of our <hi>gladneſſe</hi> hath <hi>crowned the yeere with his goodneſſe, and there hath beene no leading into captiuity, no complaining in our ſtreets.</hi> Nay, <hi>God</hi> with an higher hand, hath bleſt vs with all <hi>ſpirituall and heauenly bleſsings;</hi> hee hath giuen vs meanes to be <hi>good</hi> as well as <hi>ſafe;</hi> his Word moſt freely, which is his <hi>power to Saluation;</hi> the <hi>Preachers</hi> of his Word moſt abundantly, in number and knowledge, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all other <hi>reformed</hi> Churches. Our Land, ſhe is as a <hi>mother in Iſrael,</hi> a refuge to all the diſtreſſed members of <hi>Christ</hi> abroad: As a <hi>Queene in a vesture of Gold wrought about with diuers colours:</hi> here are the ſeates of <hi>Iustice;</hi> here the <hi>Schooles</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; here the <hi>Temples</hi> of the liuing <hi>God;</hi> the <hi>offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories</hi> of our daily prayers and praiſes; the <hi>exerciſe</hi> whereof, (beſides our priuate <hi>Soliloquies</hi>) we haue in euery <hi>Pariſh</hi> Church euery weeke thrice, in euery <hi>Cathedrall</hi> euery day thrice. Nay, ſo frequent are they in our great Cities, that euery houre of the day may bee ſpent in publike deuotion. Laſtly, as the crowne of all; <hi>God,</hi> as vpon <hi>this</hi> day, hath giuen vs a carefull <hi>Guardian</hi> of all theſe bleſſings, who ſtudies nothing more, then to make them as <hi>ſecure</hi> as they are <hi>profitable.</hi> Oh let vs take heede, that with theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21396:7"/> 
               <hi>Iſraelites</hi> here, wee rebell not againſt ſo gracious a <hi>God,</hi> ſo bounteous a <hi>Benefactor.</hi> It hath euer beene a Practick <hi>Maxime in Theology, Ingentia beneficia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia vitia, ingentia ſupplicia:</hi> Great benefits, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with foule ſinnes, and in fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And if we, through diſobedience, ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the riches of Gods grace vpon vs, what can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, but a <hi>fearefull conſummation of Iudgements</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun, that as <hi>God</hi> rent here from <hi>Saul</hi> a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſo according to our <hi>Sauiours</hi> owne prophecy, he ſhould take from vs a ſpirituall <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>conferre it vpon a people that will bring</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. 43.</note> 
               <hi>forth the fruits thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greatneſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſings being abuſed, they prooued to <hi>Iſrael</hi> here the aggrauation both of their <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>puniſhment.</hi> All which <hi>light</hi> the heauier vpon them, becauſe they did it for ſuch poore and vnworthy ends.</p>
            <p>Lord! How ſtreight a charge had God giuen them, concerning the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> though it bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of Armes, that women and children, who cannot beare Armes, ſhould be ſlaine? yet <hi>God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Samuel, bade ſmite Amalek, ſlay both man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and woman, infant and ſuckling, oxen and ſheepe.</hi> With how ſtrong a reaſon was this <hi>commiſsion</hi> backt? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how Amalek laid waite for Iſrael, in the way as they came vp from Aegypt.</hi> Here is command backt with reaſon, but all notwithſtanding, <hi>Saul</hi> and his people deſtroyed that only which was vile; <hi>but ſpared Agag the King and all that was good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conceiued motiues of which their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though many &amp; courtly, are all, in compariſon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21396:7"/> to the reward of obedience, moſt poore and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. Some thinke they did it for <hi>couetouſneſſe</hi> of the <hi>ſpoyle,</hi> and of <hi>Agags ranſome;</hi> and ſo made <hi>Mammon</hi> their <hi>god,</hi> which is expreſſe <hi>Idolatry</hi> Some<note place="margin">Phil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> coniecture, they ſpared the <hi>fatlings of the cattell,</hi> to feaſt after victory; and ſo they made their <hi>belly their</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ.</note> 
               <hi>god:</hi> and thats Idolatry. Some ſay they ſpared <hi>King Agag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that they might leade him as their vaſſall in triumph, after victory; and ſo they made their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their god: and thats flat Idolatry. At the 15. <hi>verſe</hi> it is alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dged, that they ſpared the <hi>beſt of the cattell,</hi> to ſacrifice them vnto the <hi>Lord:</hi> and ſo they made Religion a <hi>ſtalking horſe</hi> to rebellion; and thats the <hi>knowne badge</hi> of Idolatry. At the 24. <hi>verſe Saul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that he did it for <hi>feare</hi> of the people, and ſo made popular <hi>applauſe</hi> his god. Now, to worſhip a monſter with ſo many heads, is groſſe <hi>Idolatry. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> writes, he ſpared King <hi>Agag,</hi> becauſe he was a comely and a beautifull Prince; and <hi>Abule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis,</hi> that he did it out of <hi>pitty;</hi> fearing leſt the tables being turn'd, and the dice new caſt, it might one day proue his <hi>owne</hi> caſe. And ſuch indeed are oft the turnes in humane affaires: as <hi>England</hi> by computation wonne <hi>Normandy,</hi> the ſame day fortie yeeres wherein <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> ouercame <hi>England.</hi> Well, graunt which you will, or all theſe coniectures to be true: yet that <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>people,</hi> for ſuch vnworthy ends as theſe, ſhould reiect the Word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>runne a whoring after their owne inuentions,</hi> what was all this, but the worſt of Idolatry, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> Selfe-ſeruice, Sacrificing to their nets? They made<note place="margin">Col. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Abacuc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> their <hi>Pitty,</hi> their <hi>glory,</hi> their <hi>belly,</hi> their <hi>Mammon,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21396:8"/> their <hi>God,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> ſetting vp their owne <hi>ends</hi> and their owne <hi>will,</hi> aboue <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>will.</hi> And this is a lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pitch of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus foule was <hi>Sauls rebellion</hi> in the <hi>commiſsion</hi> of his fault; And if you looke with a true Chriſtian eye, either vpon his falſe <hi>excuſe,</hi> or his hypocriticall <hi>repentance;</hi> twill prooue rather <hi>worſe</hi> then <hi>better</hi> in his <hi>ſubmiſsion:</hi> for whereas <hi>obedience</hi> ſhould be no diſputant, no <hi>murmurer,</hi> no framer of <hi>excuſes;</hi> yet <hi>Saul,</hi> who would not be <hi>obeying,</hi> would be <hi>excuſing,</hi> and that with a notorious falſity, ſaying, <hi>I haue ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the Commandement of the Lord.</hi> Now, <hi>falſity</hi> is a foule fault in a <hi>man,</hi> much more in a <hi>Magiſtrate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet an vntruth ſo palpable was here defended, that the very <hi>bleating ſheep and lowing oxen</hi> confuted him. Yet ſtill the ſinne riſeth higher: for as he excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his fault <hi>falſly,</hi> ſo he <hi>repented</hi> hypocritically. How<note place="margin">v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe 14.</note> hardly could <hi>Samuel</hi> bring him to acknowledge his ſinne! and when he did it, twas a <hi>Politicke deſigne,</hi> all for vaine-glory onely; the aime of his ambition was, that the <hi>Prophet would honour him before the Elders of his people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did ſinne thruſt on ſinne, as one waue driues another. And if by theſe degrees his rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clymd not high enough to reach the ſinne of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold yet two ſteps more, by which it will arriue at the very top of it. Firſt, it was a ſinne of <hi>knowledge,</hi> not of <hi>ignorance:</hi> For he had a <hi>precept</hi> inioyned, <hi>Goe ſmite Amalek.</hi> He had a <hi>reaſon</hi> adioyned; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> that <hi>which Amaleck did, how he layed waite</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verſe 3.</note> 
               <hi>for Iſrael</hi> oft. Why behold, <hi>Abraham</hi> obeyed <hi>God</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>against</hi> reaſon; diſpenſing with all his deare and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21396:8"/> neere affections: at Gods command, ready to <hi>kill</hi> his owne and onely ſonne: yet ſee diſobedient <hi>Saul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> though he haue the <hi>Lords</hi> expreſſe <hi>warrant,</hi> backt with vnanſwerable <hi>reaſon,</hi> will to the contrary, ſpare <hi>Agag,</hi> a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> an <hi>Amalckite,</hi> a profeſt <hi>enemy</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his choſen <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, which was the pitch of his iniquity; it was not a ſin of <hi>knowledge</hi> only, but of <hi>stubbornnes;</hi> a ſinne of the <hi>will;</hi> plaine <hi>rebellion;</hi> a wilfull deſperate <hi>contumacy. Gods</hi> deareſt children fall euery day by ſinnes of <hi>infirmity;</hi> but they in their offences are <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue,</hi> rather then <hi>actiue; they doe not that which they would, they doe that which they would not.</hi> Haue they<note place="margin">Rem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but a willing minde? <hi>Why God accepts according to that a man hath.</hi> There is as great a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſtubborne <hi>preſumption</hi> and a ſlip of <hi>frailty,</hi> as betwixt <hi>murther</hi> and <hi>chance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> medly.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes it the property of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> himſelfe to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one whoſe <hi>will</hi> is his <hi>law;</hi> and his children, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, are ſtiled by the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> The ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> the <hi>ſons of perdition. Deus eſt ſua cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cupido.</hi> Of all <hi>Idolaters</hi> he is the moſt incorrigible, who makes his <hi>will</hi> his <hi>God.</hi> Euery ſiune is ſo <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> that it were no ſinne, if it were not <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi> Sinnes of <hi>infirmity</hi> are eſpecially ſaid to bee committed againſt <hi>God the Father,</hi> whoſe eſpeciall attribute is <hi>power;</hi> ſinnes of <hi>ignorance</hi> againſt <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> whoſe eſpeciall attribute is wiſedome: but ſinnes of <hi>malice</hi> are ſinnes againſt <hi>God the holy Ghoſt,</hi> whoſe eſpeciall attribute is <hi>loue.</hi> Tis ill to offend in the former; tis fearefull, with <hi>Saul</hi> and his people here, to offend in the latter kind. If therewere no <hi>wil,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21396:9"/> ſaith holy <hi>Bernard,</hi> there would be no <hi>hell.</hi> Not but that if our will be ſubiect to <hi>Gods</hi> will, it is in one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the beſt of all the ſoules faculties; it being the faculty by which we enioy all other good things. Neuer ſacrifice more acceptable to <hi>God,</hi> then that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his <hi>Father, non quod ego volo: Not as I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 39.</note> 
               <hi>will, but as thou wilt.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, nor <hi>witchcraft</hi> nor <hi>Idolatry</hi> could be more diſpleaſing to <hi>God</hi> then <hi>Sauls Rebell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on:</hi> inſomuch as <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke him, becauſe he would not forſake his owne will. <hi>Non obedire,</hi> not to haue done the will of the <hi>Lord,</hi> this might haue beene only a ſinne of <hi>errour</hi> or <hi>infirmity:</hi> but <hi>nolle obedire,</hi> (as it is here in this <hi>Text) rebelliouſly</hi> to reiect his Word, &amp; <hi>reſist</hi> his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and not to be ſo much <hi>as willing</hi> to doe his will, ſuch <hi>ſtubbornneſſe</hi> and <hi>contumacy</hi> was as the <hi>iniquity</hi> of <hi>witchcraft and Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now I am come to the very ayme of my <hi>text,</hi> and could wiſh I had no occaſion to proceed: I would to <hi>God</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> and his people were only guilty of this ſinne: but I feare (too iuſtly) that I haue beene all this while but telling our owne tale, <hi>mutato nomine de nobis fabula.</hi> I profeſſe in <hi>verbo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis,</hi> that my conſcience apprehends nothing ſo likely to prouoke yet <hi>Gods</hi> heauier Iudgements vpon this Land, then our wilfulnes and <hi>diſobedience;</hi> our <hi>ſtubbornneſſe</hi> and <hi>contumacy,</hi> firſt, againſt <hi>God</hi> in heauen: ſecondly, againſt his <hi>Deputy</hi> on earth. For the firſt; how often hath the <hi>Lord</hi> called vs by his Word? how often by his Iudgements? yet, at what eaſie rates haue we ſold our obedience to our good God?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21396:9"/>
            <p>Though <hi>Caeſar</hi> permitted a man to breake his oath, yet hee would haue it done <hi>for a kingdome. Siluester</hi> the ſecond, as <hi>Platina</hi> reported, gaue his ſoule to the diuell; but it was for a <hi>Popedome.</hi> Feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bargaines theſe! Alas, <hi>What profits it a man to winne the whole world, and to loſe his owne ſoule?</hi> Yet ſee! our contracts are more wickedly ridiculous: We wretched wormes will diſobey our <hi>God,</hi> for the leaſt intereſt of <hi>gaine;</hi> the leaſt <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> of the fleſh; the leaſt <hi>punctilio</hi> of honour; the leaſt <hi>atome</hi> of vanity; for very <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>wretched things,</hi> that vaniſh as ſmoake: and if wee compare them, either with the eternity of <hi>God</hi> in Heauen, or with the <hi>incertainty</hi> of our life on earth (<hi>things that are, as if they were not at all</hi>) yet, for their ſakes doe we become worſe then <hi>Iudas</hi> himſelfe; for hee ſold <hi>Chriſt</hi> but once, and that for <hi>thirtie pieces of ſiluer;</hi> we daily ſell him thirty times; and that ſcarce for the price of <hi>one</hi> piece. We ſinne, becauſe we will ſinne; for euery trifle, ſwearing by his precious wounds; abuſing his gracious bleſſings; being as bad as <hi>Pilate</hi> alſo, crucifying againe the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> to giue life vnto <hi>Barabbas</hi> a murtherer; that is, vnto <hi>our ſinfull will</hi> that ſlayes our ſoules. That will and heart of ours, which we ſhould giue vp to <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>luſt</hi> hath it, or our <hi>ambition:</hi> either new Wine hath<note place="margin">Hoſea 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Matth. 6. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> taken it away, or elſe <hi>where our Treaſure is, there is our heart alſo.</hi> Would we but looke conſcienciouſly into our ſelues, we ſhould finde that there are two <hi>willes</hi> in man: the will of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and the will of the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> the one from our <hi>ſelues,</hi> the other from <hi>God.</hi> If we will follow that only which is our <hi>owne,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21396:10"/> (the will of the fleſh) we are meere <hi>Monothelites,</hi> as bad as beaſts themſelues: but if wee ſubmit the will of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> to the will of the <hi>ſpirit; Tunc erit vera pax hominis, quando &amp; caro animo iudice regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; animus Deo praeſide gubernatur.</hi> Then is there perfection of happineſſe in the ſoule of man, when the fleſh is gouern'd by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> by <hi>God.</hi> At which Chriſtian perfection if wee will ayme; when God commands, we muſt not ſpare to ſlay our <hi>Agag,</hi> to mortifie our neereſt &amp; deareſt ſinnes. Nay, <hi>Obedire eſt obaudire:</hi> ſo to captiuate our wils to <hi>God,</hi> that we muſt heare him not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> but againſt our ſelues too: And that not only in <hi>proſperity,</hi> but in <hi>aduerſity</hi> alſo: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we ſhall be like a bow, which will bend in the belly only, but not in the backe. In a word, <hi>Obedience to God</hi> is a Royall Sacrifice; <hi>The feare of the Lord, is the glory of the King.</hi> Though Kings<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.</note> haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the will of the ſubiects vnder them; yet <hi>God</hi> hath the will of <hi>Kings</hi> vnder him. Though <hi>Kings</hi> be <hi>Gods</hi> before men, yet, they are but <hi>men</hi> before <hi>God;</hi> though <hi>Gods</hi> on earth, yet, but <hi>Gods</hi> of earth; ſubiects to the <hi>God</hi> of Heauen. <hi>God</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth one <hi>King</hi> by the death of another, to let vs know, that the liuing King depends vpon the liuing God: <hi>Though yee are the children of the moſt high,</hi> yet, <hi>yee ſhall die like men, Pſal.</hi> 82. No foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a King ſo ſure, as <hi>obedience</hi> to him that made him <hi>King.</hi> No Sacrifice ſo acceptable, as for the King to lay downe his will at Gods Altar. As nothing more hatefull in a ſubiect then <hi>rebellion</hi> to his <hi>King:</hi> So nothing more dangerous in a <hi>King,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21396:10"/> then <hi>rebellion</hi> to <hi>God: but if the King trusts in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 21. 7.</note> 
               <hi>mercy of the Lord, he ſhall not ſlide.</hi> For he giueth deliuerance to Kings, and reskues <hi>Dauid</hi> his ſeruant<note place="margin">Pſal. 144. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from the hurtfull ſword.</p>
            <p>Nor doth the benefit of <hi>Royall obedience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> redound to the <hi>King</hi> alone; the King by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe<note place="margin">Prou. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> maintaines the Countrey. <hi>Foelix Reſpub: in qua qui imperat, timet Deum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iuſtin;</hi> How long hath our owne happy experience demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vs, That the Piety of the <hi>King,</hi> is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the <hi>Common-wealth?</hi> Nor can we iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget the happineſſe of this Day, wherein our owne ſoules know, that God hath enlarged vs the continuance of this vnualewable bleſsing, a moſt Pious <hi>Sonne,</hi> ſucceeding a moſt Religious <hi>Father.</hi> Tis not with vs, where the <hi>King</hi> obeyes the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> his <hi>Rector,</hi> the <hi>Rector</hi> his <hi>Generall,</hi> his <hi>Generall</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> his owne <hi>Traditions,</hi> aboue the Oracles of <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> reſolues with <hi>Dauid, I will hearken what the Lord God will ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 8</note> 
               <hi>mee.</hi> To which end, how conſtant is <hi>He</hi> in his priuate, how frequent in <hi>His</hi> publick Deuotions? how reuerend in <hi>His</hi> geſtures? how exemplary in <hi>His</hi> life? Yee cannot count that flattery; which our iuſt comfort, and which the duty of the Day cals for. If <hi>Regis ad exemplum</hi> be a good rule, can the Kingdome find out a better Maſter to teach the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, Religion? the glutton, temperance? the drunkard, ſobriety? the prophaner, ſanctity? the laſciuious, chaſtity? the Idolater, Purity? Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as would the <hi>ſubiects</hi> well learne their <hi>Kings</hi> leſſon, we could not haue ſuch cauſe to feare the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21396:11"/> wrath of <hi>God</hi> in the proſecution of his iudgements vpon vs: ſince the <hi>Obedience</hi> and Piety of this <hi>our holy Guardian</hi> ſtands like the <hi>good Angell,</hi> like <hi>Moſes in the gap, to diuert Gods plagues from vs.</hi> Oh, that therefore <hi>His</hi> example, and the conſideration of our <hi>owne</hi> good, would mooue vs to expreſſe our thankfulneſſe in our <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> firſt and chiefly!</p>
            <p>Secondly, and by a true rule of <hi>ſubordination to Gods Deputy</hi> our <hi>King.</hi> To which we are not onely ſweetly inuited by his <hi>goodnes,</hi> but vndenyably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by the rule of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Gods Christs on earth,</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt cals them,) They are neither from <hi>Pope</hi> nor people, as ſome would haue it; but hold in <hi>Capite</hi> immediately from <hi>God: By me Kings raigne.</hi> If with <hi>Iſrael</hi> thou reiecteſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerbs 8. 15. 1 Samuel 8. 7.</note> thou reiecteſt <hi>God</hi> himſelfe. I know there is a generation, who thinke themſelues bound by their holy profeſſion, to quit ſubiects from their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; to authoriſe the depoſition, nay, the murther of Kings; with <hi>Pope Sixtus Quintus,</hi> to iuſtify trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and parricides, as <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>memorable</hi> Acts. <hi>God</hi> forbid any ſuch <hi>Zimries</hi> or <hi>Doegs</hi> ſhould lurke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the tents of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Goſpell</hi> cannot ſuffer vs to ſwell to this height of rebellion. Yet, that wee may not too much ouer-valew our ſelues, giue mee leaue to wiſh; I would there were none among vs, who place their <hi>conſcience</hi> too much in their <hi>will;</hi> who are all for <hi>faith</hi> and the <hi>firſt</hi> table, nothing for <hi>obedience</hi> and the <hi>ſecond</hi> table. I would there were none to tell vs, that to <hi>obey</hi> our <hi>Prince,</hi> is to <hi>betray</hi> our <hi>country;</hi> none, who ſtampe it as a maine brand
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21396:11"/> vpon the <hi>Clergy,</hi> That <hi>they preach obedience.</hi> Well, Chriſtians, let it be more <hi>practiſed,</hi> I dare promiſe that it will be leſſe <hi>preached.</hi> Whence we that preach it, haue our warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I am ſure: but in what Catechiſm theſe men learne their religion, I know not. From <hi>Rome</hi> they are aſhamed to take it; from Conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">In Eſay cap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi> they could not, who tells vs that the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſecond table is the true touch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtone of hypocrites.</hi> Much leſſe from Iudicious <hi>Luther,</hi> who profeſt in a point of <hi>Canonicall</hi> obedience, <hi>Mallem obedire, quàm miracula facere:</hi> That he had rather o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, then doe miracles. And therefore theſe men, who will doe nothing without Text, might find Text enough for their obedience, not onely in my Text here, but in 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2. Chapter, where they are enioyned <hi>to obey for the Lords ſake:</hi> and for <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake,</hi> in the 13. to the <hi>Romanes</hi> 2. where <hi>to diſobey</hi> is <hi>damnation.</hi> In the whole current of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where we find that for mans <hi>diſobedience,</hi> the peſtilence hath deuoured them; Fire from heauen hath conſumed them; The earth hath opened her mouth and ſwallowed them. <hi>Filthy dreamers</hi> (as holy <hi>Iude</hi> cals them) <hi>who deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeake euill</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>of Dignities, woe vnto them: for they haue periſhed in the gaine-ſaying of</hi> Core: <hi>Raging waues of the ſea, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out their owne ſhame, to whom is reſerued the blacknes of darkenes for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the ſpeech of a man renowned for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in our age, That if he were commanded to put forth to the ſea in a ſhip that had neither maſt nor tackling, he would doe it. And being asked what wiſedome that were? replied, The wiſedome muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21396:12"/> be in Him that hath power to command, not in him that conſcience bindes to obey.</p>
            <p>Heare yet a wiſer then he. <hi>My Sonne, feare God and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 24. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and meddle not with them who are giuen to change: for their calamity will riſe ſuddainly, and who knowes the ruine of them?</hi> To conclude; pretend theſe men what they will, <hi>Sine obedientia quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> infidelis eſſe conuincitur.</hi> S. <hi>Gregory</hi> had no faith <hi>in their</hi> faith who profeſt againſt <hi>obedience. Nemo humanam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatem contemnit, niſi qui prius Diuinam contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</hi> No man hath learn'd to diſobey his <hi>King,</hi> but he had learn'd before to diſobey his <hi>God.</hi> Oh, let vs all therefore take heed, That while we <hi>flye</hi> from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> we runne not into <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Farre be it from vs to be found <hi>with Iſrael</hi> a <hi>diſobedient and gain-ſaying people.</hi> But as <hi>God</hi> with one hand, hath as vpon <hi>this Day,</hi> deriued to vs an <hi>Inualewable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> a true <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> and <hi>Protector</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> a <hi>King</hi> reſolued to purſue <hi>Amalek,</hi> who hath ſo often <hi>laid in waite for Iſrael:</hi> ſo let vs with another hand offer on the <hi>ſame Day,</hi> the beſt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, <hi>Obedience. Obedience to God,</hi> who hath bleſt vs with ſuch a <hi>King: Obedience</hi> to our <hi>King,</hi> who is ſuch an example of <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, Let vs pray for our ſelues, that wee may <hi>reſiſt</hi> all ſinne, eſpecially <hi>preſumptuous ſinne,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Rebellion,</hi> The ſinne paralell to <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi> And let vs pray for our <hi>King,</hi> that wee long and conſtantly <hi>obeying Him,</hi> and <hi>Hee</hi> long and conſtantly <hi>obeying God;</hi> may <hi>liue</hi> and <hi>proſper</hi> in the fauour of <hi>God,</hi> and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21396:12"/> 
               <hi>loue</hi> of <hi>his ſubiects;</hi> to the confuſion of our mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aduerſaries, and to the glory of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> This graunt, O Thou eternall <hi>King of Kings, God</hi> the <hi>Father, Sonne, and holy Ghost;</hi> to whom eternall <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>Vnity;</hi> be all Praiſe, Power, Glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
